<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A declaration against a late dangerous and seditious band, under the name of An humble remonstrance, &amp;c. wherein the plots and projects of the contrivers tending to the violating and subversion of our covenants; raising and fomenting of jealousies, within this, and between both kingdoms; prolonging of the unnaturall wars; and, impeding the intended uniformity in religion, are discovered, / by the Commission of the General Assembly.</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1646</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 28 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A82033</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D519</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E330_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R200712</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861381</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861381</idno>
            <idno type="VID">113514</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A82033)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 113514)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 54:E330[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A declaration against a late dangerous and seditious band, under the name of An humble remonstrance, &amp;c. wherein the plots and projects of the contrivers tending to the violating and subversion of our covenants; raising and fomenting of jealousies, within this, and between both kingdoms; prolonging of the unnaturall wars; and, impeding the intended uniformity in religion, are discovered, / by the Commission of the General Assembly.</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly. Commission.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>by Evan Tyler, printer to the Kings most Excellent Majesty.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1646.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March 31".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland. --  General Assembly --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  Church history --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:113514:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DECLARATION Againſt A late dangerous and ſeditious BAND, under the name of <hi>An humble Remonſtrance, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein The Plots and Projects of the Contrivers <hi>Tending to the</hi> Violating and ſubverſion of our Covenants; Raiſing and fomenting of Jealouſies, within this, and between both Kingdoms; Prolonging of the unnaturall Wars; And, Impeding the intended Uniformity in RELIGION, Are diſcovered, By the Commiſsion of the Generall Aſſembly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed at Edinburgh by</hi> Evan Tyler, <hi>Printer to the Kings moſt Excellent Majeſty.</hi> 1646.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license">
            <pb facs="tcp:113514:2"/>
            <head>Edinb. Penult. Martii 1646.</head>
            <p>THe Commiſsioners of the Generall Aſſembly Do Ordain this Declaration to be forthwith Printed and publiſhed, and ſent to Presbyteries with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence: Requiring each Presbytery immediatly after the receit thereof, to take ſpeedie courſe for the reading of it in every congregation within their bounds upon the Lords day after the Forenoon Sermon and before the Bleſsing; And that they report account of their diligence herein with the firſt conveniencie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:113514:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Edinb. Penult. Martii</hi> 1646. A DECLARATION againſt a late dangerous and ſeditious Band, under the name of <hi>An humble Remonſtrance, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen we conſider the uſuall way of Gods wiſe diſpenſation toward his people, in exerciſing them with one trouble after another, and call to minde the inveterate malice of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan and his inſtruments, and their inceſſant practiſes to pervert the ſtraight wayes of the Lord; We do not think it ſtrange, while we are ſtill wreſtling with former difficulties, and under hope of prevailing by the mighty help of Gods right hand, that we are infeſted with new aſſaults, from which <hi>he who hath delivered us from ſo great troubles, and doth deliver us, in him we truſt that he will deliver us:</hi> Yet perceiving by a Paper come to our hands, carrying the Title of <hi>An humble Remonſtrance, &amp;c.</hi> the indeavours of ſome to deceive the ſimple,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:113514:3"/> and to inſinuate wicked counſels and courſes under the cover of ſpecious pretences, We judge our ſelves oblieged, out of conſcience of the truſt committed unto us, according to the conſtant and commendable practiſe of the Commiſſioners of the Generall Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly in the like exigences, To unmask the face of diſguiſed impiety, to diſcover the myſterie of Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and to <hi>bring to light the hidden things of diſhoneſty,</hi> that they who through ignorance or inadvertencie have been drawn away into the errour of the wicked, may be reduced, the ſimple preſerved from ſeducti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the weak ſtrengthened, the ſtrong confirmed, and the wicked, if poſſible, made aſhamed of their wayes.</p>
            <p>It is ordinary in the Title of Remonſtrances, to deſigne the perſons to whom they are directed, but this doth altogether abſtain from all deſignation of that kind, though the Remonſtrants knew that there were Judicatories both Civil and Eccleſiaſticall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by Parliament and Generall Aſſemblie, to whoſe conſideration belonged matters of ſuch pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like concernment for Kirk and State; whereby they evidence their neglect and contempt of theſe, and their warineſſe to offend them who are in open Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, unto whom it is likely they labour to apply themſelves; ſince there is nothing in the whole Paper excluding them, but by the contrary clear inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their deſire and deſigne to have them parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the publike Peace.</p>
            <p>The flouriſh of the fair deſcription they arrogate to themſelves, as being ſuch <hi>who wiſh Religion to flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, &amp;c.</hi> is not ſufficient to free them from the ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:113514:3"/> of thoſe who by their barbarous and bloody cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes have bin ſubverting Religion, &amp; the Kings lawful authority, deſtroying the Subjects and their lawfull Liberties, and fomenting the unhappy differences between the King and his people; for <hi>James Grahame</hi> himſelf is a pretender to all theſe as well as they: And we know that ſome, who are prime Leaders in the buſineſſe, had not onely their hand at that Band which did make the firſt breach upon the Unity made by our Nationall Covenant, and was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as unlawfull by the Generall Aſſembly holden at <hi>Edinburgh</hi> 1641. <hi>Seſſ.</hi> 17. But alſo after the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture and Excommunication of the before-named Traitour, did in the yeer 1645 ſubſcribe a Band of Union with him and others, as his Majeſties faithfull Subjects, without mention of, or relation to any of the Covenants, whether Nationall, or of the three Kingdomes; wherein the power and Commiſſion granted to the ſaid <hi>James Grahame,</hi> there deſigned <hi>James</hi> Marqueſſe of Montroſe, his Majeſties Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant-Generall, is acknowledged and approven; and the publike reſolutions of Kirk and Kingdome are blaſphemed, as the horrid courſes of a Rebellious fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction raging within this Kingdome, as moſt wicked and Traiterous, unjuſt and unnaturall, and as of a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe faction of deſperate Rebels, in fury againſt the King; Oblieging themſelves to uſe all their beſt and moſt vigorous oppoſition againſt the Actors and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments thereof, as of abominable and monſtrous crimes, and mutually to aſſiſt one another, as they ſhall be deſired, or the occaſion require. Which are enough to render their by-wayes hatefull to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:113514:4"/> well-affected, though they be ſtrawed with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Pietie and publike good.</p>
            <p>Becauſe the Nationall Aſſembly hath found and declared, that the Band forementioned, and all Bands of that and the like nature, may not lawfully be made: And the Eſtates of Parliament <hi>Parl.</hi> 3. of King <hi>Charles, Act</hi> 4. findes that perſons guilty of taking up Armes againſt the Kingdome and Eſtates of the Countrey, are puniſhable by forfeiture of Life, lands, goods, or any other cenſure the Parliament ſhall pleaſe to inflict. Theſe Remonſtrants, leſt people ſhould be ſcarred from acceſſion to their combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by the authority of Parliament and Generall Aſſembly, have laboured to cover the nature of this Paper, under the name of <hi>An humble Remonſtrance;</hi> which nevertheles is ſo tranſparent, that every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary eye may ſee it in the end, a Band oblieging them each to others, and that by an Oath, <hi>To hazard Lives and Fortunes againſt all deadly</hi> for performing all the contents; whereby the Subſcribers thereof become lyable to the cenſures and puniſhments which the Kirk and State may inflict upon them for unlawfull Banding and raiſing Arms againſt the Kingdom.</p>
            <p>Although they mention the Nationall Covenant, and declare their reſolution <hi>of paying the debt they owe to the individuals</hi> (which we conceive to be the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, or ſeverall Articles) therein contained; yet we cannot but affirme, that their charity is too too common who beleeve at all their deceitfull profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſince the whole ſtrain of their Remonſtrance is an <hi>evident Demonſtration of their monſtrous defection.</hi> For, 1. Their altering of the words of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:113514:4"/> argues their purpoſe to ſwerve from the true meaning of it. The Covenant bindes to the defence of the Doctrine and Diſcipline of this Kirk; they ſay they purpoſe to do <hi>what may moſt tend for the propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Proteſtant Religion in purity,</hi> a phraſe uſed in the Kings Declarations, wherein he profeſſeth the maintenance of Epiſcopacie: The Covenant ſpeaks of the defence of the Kings Majeſties perſon and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, in the defence and preſervation of the true Religion, Liberties, and Lawes of this Kingdome; they, <hi>of the defence of the Kings Majeſties juſt Right and Property,</hi> and that ſimply and abſolutely, without any ſuch relation to Religion, Liberties, &amp; Laws; The Covenant, of the Laws and Liberties of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; they, <hi>of the lawfull proper Freedoms and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the Subjects.</hi> 2. Among other <hi>Individuals</hi> of the Covenant, this is one, That neither directly nor indirectly ſhall we ſuffer our ſelves to be divided or withdrawn, by whatſoever ſuggeſtion, combina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, allurement, or terrour, from that bleſſed and loyall conjunction: But they have directly divided and withdrawn themſelves from that bleſſed and loyall conjunction, wherein the Kirk and Kingdom continue conſtant, by a cleer combination in writ un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their hands. 3. Another particular in the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant is, That we ſhall not caſt in any let or impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that may ſtay or hinder any ſuch reſolution as by common conſent ſhall be found to conduce for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o good ends: But they obliege themſelves to hinder reſolutions found by common conſent of the Eſtates of Parliament, to conduce for the ends mentioned in the Covenant, ſuch as the keeping on foot Armies
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:113514:5"/> at home and abroad, and all means for their neceſſary maintenance.</p>
            <p>The ſolemne League and Covenant, unanimouſly approven by the Generall Aſſemblies of this Kirk, ratified by the authoritie of the Parliament of this Kingdome, and univerſally ſworn and ſubſcribed through the Kirks of this Kingdome, is not ſo much as once remembred in this Remonſtrance; yea clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough to a perceiving beholder, though warily and cloſely they exclude the ſame, while they call the Nationall Covenant <hi>Approven,</hi> as if the other were not approven, and while they deny a <hi>deſire of diſſolving the link of fraternitie betwixt us and our Brethren of England,</hi> inſinuating their diſavowing of a League and Covenant of fraternitie; Otherwiſe they would not have ſhunned the mention of the League and Covenant, when they had ſo fair an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion offered of expreſſing their approbation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, as a tye of our unitie with our Brethren in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land: So that the ſubſcription of this Band brings with it a fearfull breach of the League and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</p>
            <p>Unitie and Uniformitie in Religion and Kirk go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſo much preſſed by our Commiſſioners, as a ſpeciall means for conſerving the Peace betwixt the two Kingdomes, upon the grounds and reaſons contained in their Paper of the 10. of March 1641. and given in to the Treatie and Parliament of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land; ſo much promoved by the continued labours of the following Generall Aſſemblies, and their Commiſſioners from time to time, both at home, and at London; to the endeavouring whereof we are
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:113514:5"/> ſo ſtrongly engaged by the League and Covenant of the Kingdome, and which is ſo far advanced in the Directory for Worſhip, agreed upon by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, and ratified by the Parliaments in both Kingdomes, is utterly neglected, and not ſo much as mentioned in this ſeditious Band.</p>
            <p>What is here offered by them to the view of the world, if it be looked upon with the eye of any, but ſuch as have given themſelves to a deteſtable indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferencie &amp; neutralitie in this cauſe, wherein the Kirk and Kingdom are engaged, ſhall be found fraughted with the Characters, ſet down in the ſolemne and ſeaſonable Warning of the Generall Aſſembly, holden at Edinburgh 1645. whereby ſecret Malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants and diſ-covenanters may be known, ſuch are, Their ſlighting and cenſuring of the Publick Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutions of this Kirk and State Art. 3. and 4. Their la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring to raiſe jealouſies and diviſions, to retard or hinder the execution of what is ordered by publick Judicatories, Art. 5. Their cenſuring and ſlandering theſe whom GOD hath honoured as his chief In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments in this Work, Art. 2. and 3. Their draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Parties and Factions, to the weakning of the Common Union in their concluſion; Their endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, Informations, and Solicitations, tending to weaken the hearts and hands of others, and to make them with-hold their aſſiſtance from this Work, which is the very ſcope of their 6. Article.</p>
            <p>The Article of Inviting the Kings Majeſtie into this his Native Kingdom, though it ſeem plauſible a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the firſt hearing, and for that cauſe firſt placed: Yet let it be pondered by ſecond thoughts (which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:113514:6"/> are the wiſeſt) in the ſcales of reaſon, and the preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice thereof ſhall clearly appear. For 1. he who conſidereth that much innocent blood of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties good Subjects hath been ſhed by his Majeſties Commands and Commiſſions, Iriſh Rebels have been brought over into both Kingdomes, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to bring over more; as alſo Forces from forreigne parts; That his Majeſty is in open hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt the Parliament of England, Forces on foot by his Majeſties Commiſſion, againſt the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Scotland, under the leading of that accurſed and forfaulted Traitour, and the Warre in Ireland fomented and prolonged by his Majeſty; whereby the three Kingdomes are brought neer to utter ruine and deſtruction, Shall perceive, that untill ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ſecuritie be firſt given to both Kingdoms, his Majeſties coming hither cannot be convenient, nor called for. Upon which ground, the Parliament of England, and the Commiſſioners of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Scotland, in their Letter to his Majeſty; Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuary 13. 1646. refuſe the perſonall Treaty deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by his Majeſty, and declare, That Propoſitions from both Kingdomes are to be ſent to his Majeſty, which they conceive (far otherwayes, and upon ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer ground then theſe Banders do) to be the onely way for attaining a happy and wel-grounded Peace. 2. Such an invitation for making Peace, may not proceed from this Kingdome, without the advice and conſent of our neighbour Kingdom, with which we are entred in League and Covenant (far leſſe from a few private perſons, banded in this Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance) unleſſe we will directly break the 8. Article
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:113514:6"/> of the Treaty, ratified in the 3. <hi>Parl.</hi> of King <hi>Charles, Act</hi> 5. wherein it is agreed and concluded, That no ceſſation, nor pacification, or agreement for Peace whatſomever, ſhall be made by either Kingdome, or the Armies of either Kingdomes, without the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall advice and conſent of both Kingdomes, or their Committees in that behalf appointed, who are to have full power for the ſame, in caſe the Parliament or Convention of the Eſtates of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ſhall not ſit. 3. This In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitation and incoming of the Kings Majeſty, while he is ſtill in terms of Hoſtility againſt his Parliament of England, is ſo far from ſetling a ſolid Peace (as they confidently conceive) that it will undoubtedly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long theſe unnaturall Warres, and draw upon this Land the heavieſt weight, and deepeſt dint of them.</p>
            <p>Theſe Judicatories, the re-eſtabliſhment whereof is deſired by their third Article, have neither been al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together ſilent, For ſome of them have ſit and kept their diets of meeting; Neither yet have bin ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenced by men (as they do inſinuate) but have been neceſſarily interrupted through the Invaſion of the barbarous Iriſhes, and Inſurrection of diſ-natured Countrymen, and through the ſpreading and raging of the fearful Plague of Peſtilence, and now by ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of Parliament they are to meet again at the ordinary times, if the like cauſes do not neceſſitate an unexpected vacation. In the mean time it is to be remembred, that Judicatories authoriſed by Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with ſuch power as the condition of affairs, &amp; the neceſſity of theſe preſent times required, were
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:113514:7"/> not ſilent, though ſome of theſe Remonſtrants would not hearken to them; Or elſe they had been more active againſt the publike Enemies, which had made a fairer way for opening the Ordinary Judica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories, than the ſtrengthening of the bloodie hands of the Rebels unto the works of violence, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triving a Band.</p>
            <p>The danger of weakning the Kingdome, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring it a prey to forraigners repreſented in the third Article, is increaſed by this courſe which they have taken; The Kingdome being thereby made the more unable, not onely to reſiſt forraigne Invaſion, but alſo to ſuppreſſe the Inteſtine Rebellion, while it doth not onely want their aſsiſtance, but findeth their reſiſtance. The beſt way of ſtrengthening and ſecuring the Kingdome, is, To joyne unanimouſly and actively, in purſuit of the Rebels within the ſame, whoſe garments have been dyed in the blood of the People of GOD; To entertain a firm Peace and Union between the two Kingdomes, for proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting the ends of our League and Covenant; But above all, To turn every man from his evill wayes, and to return unto him that hath ſmitten us, who can heale us, and humble our Adverſaries, and turn his hand againſt our Enemies: <hi>Our help is in the Name of the Lord, who made the heaven and the earth, With whom it is nothing to help with many, or with them that have no power; through him we ſhall do valiantly, and he ſhall tread down our enemies:</hi> Which are the precious words of GOD, and not the ſpecious phraſes of men.</p>
            <p>The fourth Article. 1. Laboureth by reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:113514:7"/> expreſſions, To make odious unto the people the beſt wayes and means that the Eſtates of Parliament and Committees thereof could think upon, for the neceſſary maintenance of Warre againſt the wicked Rebels; Whereby they caſt in a let and impediment to hinder publike Reſolutions (though ſome of theſe have of all others leaſt cauſe to complaine) and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime the neceſſity of maintaining an Army againſt <hi>James Grahame,</hi> which will affoord him and his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices leave to gather ſtrength; For the Enemy can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuppreſſed without a competent number of Forces, and Forces cannot be kept together without maintenance, and maintenance cannot be had with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch publike burdens. 2. Mentioneth the exact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of great Fines and Intromiſſions with mens For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes and Rents, whereby they evidence their favour to, and indeavour to conciliat the favour and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of ſuch as have been ſo dealt with by the Eſtates, for being acceſſory, leſſe or more, unto the unnaturall and bloody Rebellion: And, 3. Maketh a lie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Eſtates, as if they had received great ſums of money from other Kingdoms or Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealths than <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If theſe who have been moſt active in this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bination had been preſent in Parliament, they would have been witneſſes of the care taken by the Eſtates to give full ſatisfaction to every one who deſired to be informed of the publike expences &amp; disburſments, by appointing a particular Committee for examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the publike Compts, and thereafter cauſing keep the Book of Accounts in a publike Chamber, with intimation of free acceſſe to all that pleaſed:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:113514:8"/> But they are willingly if not wilfully ignorant, and bewray their diſaffection, by apprehending all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable appearance to raiſe and foment Jealouſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parliament and the Countrey and Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, which is the drift of the 5. Article.</p>
            <p>The large laying forth of the diſtreſſed condition of this Kingdome, inſiſted upon in the 6. Article, aimes at the diſcouraging and weakning of the hearts and hands of the well-affected, and tends to perſwade the disbanding our Forces imployed againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, which expoſeth what is reſerved from the fury of the Enemy, to be preyed upon by them without oppoſition: But if they, as becomes Covenanters and Countreymen, had conſidered that the moſt of thoſe calamities have been cauſed by the cruelty of the Iriſh crew, and the reſt of that Traiterous Company, and by the lukewarmneſſe, temporizing, and double dealing of hollow-hearted men, they would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved againſt all difficulties to cleave unto the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, in the purſuit and ſuppreſſing of theſe children of Belial, as a compendious way to the removall of diſtreſſes. Shall they have Lives and Fortunes to hazard againſt all deadly, for reſcuing theſe Rebells from their deſerved puniſhment? And is there no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left unto the Kingdome to hazard for its own defence, and bringing Malignants unto their due cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, according to our League and Covenant? And if the condition of our affaires crave aſſiſtance from our Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> we are confident they will be mindful of our mutuall ingagements, though theſe Banders like bad husband-men, labour to ſow the ſeeds of Jealouſies amongſt us.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:113514:8"/>
            <p>In the 7. they covertly calumniate the prime managers of affairs, as men indiſpoſed to Peace, who have abundantly evidenced their earneſt deſire of Peace, by Supplications, Remonſtrances, Declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Treaties for Peace, Propoſitions of Peace. And we further declare and profeſſe, in the ſight of him who ſearcheth the heart, That nothing is more in the deſire of us all, then that Reformed Religion may be enjoyed, with a happy and well-grounded Peace, through all his Majeſties Dominions: And from the beginning of theſe troubles, we have been cloathed with, and yet will not put off a reſolution to uſe (as we have been ever uſing) all poſſible and lawfull means to procure the ſame. And for this effect we beſeech all men, who love the Cauſe of God, and their Countreys good, to diveſt themſelves of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate quarrels and particular intereſts, that with the greater unanimitie and hope of ſucceſſe, they may purſue the troublers of our Peace. But we do inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuouſly acknowledge, That our ſouls abhor to enter into the ſecret, and our glory to be joyned with the aſſembly of them who ſue for ſuch a Peace as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehends the prime authors of all our troubles, and would ſuffer theſe who have ſhed the blood of War in Peace to go in peace into the grave.</p>
            <p>As in the entry, ſo toward the end, that the hook of the Band may the better take with well-meaning men, they busk it with great variety of fair colours; and like the harlot, they deck the bed with coverings of tapiſtry, carved works, and fine linnen; they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fume it with myrrhe and cynamon, and with impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent face, they ſpeak of Peace-offerings and paying
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:113514:9"/> their Vows; that with much fair ſpeech they may cauſe the ſimple ones to yeeld, and with the flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of their lips, force them: But he that hath un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding will diſcern that this their Profeſſion is contrary to their intent formerly diſcovered, will learn not to be credulous unto them, who ſpeak lies in hypocriſie, and not ſuffer his heart to decline to their wayes, and go aſtray in their paths which go down to the chambers of death; The repetition of their intention here, giveth them not one grain weight of truth and realitie more than they had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
            <p>Theſe Banders are not all of the ſame kind and diſpoſition of heart: Some of them have joyned in actuall and open Rebellion, and embrued their hands in the blood of their Countreymen: Theſe if they had truely forſaken that unhappy conjunction, would have ere now, or will now at length forſaking this combination apply themſelves to Kirk and State for reconciliation; which if they do not ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily go about, they manifeſt to the world, that they ſtill perſiſt in their former Rebellion, and proſecute the ſame wicked practices. Some there be, who have by ſome acts, and by ſome omiſſions of action when opportunitie was offered, brought themſelves under the ſuſpition of Malignancie: And theſe if they continue in this b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nded courſe make it evident, that they have been lying in wait for the ſeaſon when they might vent their malignant deſignes, and do involve themſelves under the diſpleaſure of God, and cenſures of the Kirk. Others there are, who have joyned in this Remonſtrance (to judge charitably)
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:113514:9"/> not out of a minde to oppoſe the Cauſe of GOD, having done and ſuffered ſo much, and hazarded all for the ſame: But partly out of their reſpect to their friends, to whom they have naturall and particular tyes; partly preſſed with the apprehenſion of ſome preſent perill, or greater evill conceived to enſue up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on refuſall; and partly deceived by the ſpecious pretences in the Remonſtrance, not conſidering the bad intentions of the Contrivers, nor the dangerous importance and conſequence of it in it ſelf. Theſe, we expect, when they conſider the condition of the Work (laid forth before them in this our Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and the quality of the Company with whom they joyne, leſt they wrong themſelves and the Work of GOD, contrary to their deſires, and more than they are aware of, will without longer deliberation or delay, renounce that banding Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, and with all convenient diligence, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint the Kirk and State with their ſenſe of that eſcape, and with their reſolution not to ſuffer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves hereafter to be divided or with-drawn, by whatſomever ſuggeſtion, combination, perſwaſion, or terrour, from the Nationall Covenant, and from the ſolemne League and Covenant of the three Kingdomes; Which will bring peace to their own mindes, and joy to the hearts of the Godly, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore them to the place which they have had in the eſteem of all that love the welfare of Zion.</p>
            <p>Having thus declared our thoughts concerning that diviſive Band, and theſe who are joyned toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in it, We exhort and warn all the people of God
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:113514:10"/> in this Land, and theſe eſpecially who have it in Commiſſion to reveal his arm to this generation, To obſerve them who cauſe diviſions and offences, and to avoid them; To keep themſelves free from appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of, or adhering to this Remonſtrance, the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe whereof is now ſo plainely pointed forth; and as one man, with one minde, according to both our Covenants, unto the utmoſt of their power to oppoſe the ſpreading of it, and the endeavours of ſuch as pertinaciouſly perſiſt therein. Let us all follow on to ſeek the Lord, and let the Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Iſrael rouze up themſelves and others, and ſtrive to get their own, and their Peoples hearts deeply affected under the feeling of the great burden both of the Sins of the Land, and of the wrath upon it. Let every one turne from the evill of his wayes, and crying mightily to GOD, give him no reſt, till he repent of the evill, ſmell a ſavour of reſt, and ſay, It is enough. And we are confident in him, who hath done all our Works for us, That no ſuch courſes or counſell ſhall proſper, as tend directly or indirectly to the breach of both, or either Covenants, to the ſtopping of the courſe of the Goſpell, to the ſtrengthening of the hands of the Wicked, or to the ſuppreſsion of Religion and Reformation; And that GOD all-ſufficient, againſt all impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments, ſhall carry forward and perfect the bleſſed and glorious Work which he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, to the glory of his great Name, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of the Kingdome of his Son JESUS
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:113514:10"/> CHRIST, to the deſtruction of Antichriſt, to the confuſion of all deſperate and irrecoverable Malignants, and to the firme Peace and happy Union in Religion of all the Dominions of his Majeſty; For whom wee ſhall ſtill continue our Prayers, That GOD would graciouſly incline his heart to the counſels of Truth and Peace, that we may live under him a peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and quiet life, in all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe and honeſtie.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. Ker.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
